A Guide to the Lydia Maria Child Collection
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #7500
Lydia Maria Child Collection 1844-1879
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
7500
ca. 25 items
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research
Acquisition Information
Gift, May 9, 1964.
Item List
- MANUSCRIPTS
  - "A mouse can drink... ", 1850 July; AMsS, 1 p.
    [Copy of Chinese proverb with added comment.]
  - "The greatest danger... ", 1861 Feb 7; AMsS, 1 p.
  - "Milan Cathedral, lifting... ", 1871; AMsS, 1 p.
  - "The human family are... ", 1876; AMsS, 1 p.
  - "The best rule for good manners... ", 1879; AMsS, 1 p.
- LETTERS
  - Lydia Maria Child to John Sullivan Dwight, 1844 Apr 23; ALS, 4 p.
    [Re mutual admiration of Norwegian violinist Ole Bull; compares with Vieux Temps (sic). Discusses the opera,
    "I Puritani;"
    makes references to Cromwell's army, Bellini, and Calvinism. People mentioned are Parke Godwin, William Henry Channing, George Ripley, Charles Anderson Dana, Friend Hopper, and John Hopper. ]
  - Lydia Maria Child to Anthony Philip Heinrich, 1845 Jun 7; ALS, 4 p.
    [Re music and its effect on her. Discusses Ole Bull at length. Refers to Jean-Jacques Rousseau and Ludwig van Beethoven. ]
  - Lydia Maria Child to Pliny Earle, 1847 Oct. 18; ALS, 1 p.
    [Requests delivery of enclosed note to Jane Bacon. ]
  - Lydia Maria Child to Oliver Johnson, 1858 Jul 28; ALS, 2 p.
    [Refuses a request to contribute to a paper, as
    Atlantic Monthly
    has made earlier request. Mentions death of Ellis Gray Loring, and a meeting of Progressive Friends. ]
  - Lydia Maria Child to Thomas Wentworth Higginson, 1859 Jul 4; ALS, 4 p.
    [Mentions sorrow at the anniversary of the death of Ellis Gray Loring. Requests pamphlet on Spiritualism. Refers to William Lloyd Garrison as a reformer. Mentions Mrs. Darrah, an artist, who is anti-slavery; mentions Republican party, and wishes that the Southern States would separate themselves from the North; and mentions a Miss [?] Parmenter.]
  - Lydia Maria Child to Richard Henry Stoddard, 1867 Jun 30; ALS, 2 p.
    [Praises Richard Henry Stoddard's verses for their feeling but not for their skill. Her autographs of Rufus Wilmot Griswold and others given to Sanitary Fairs during the War. Letter sold by Charles S. Francis, Bookseller.]
  - Lydia Maria Child to Thomas Wentworth Higginson, 1867 Sep 24; ALS, 4 p.
    [Re correspondence with C. B. Peckham about
    Religious Ideas
    , and a copy for the Free Public Library. Mentions that her sister-in-law, Lydia B. Child, is a "zealous Millerite."]
  - Lydia Maria Child to Mr. Purvis, 1868 Aug 14; ALS, 4 p.
    [Discusses anti-slavery romance novel she has written; discusses prejudice and colored people. Compares current prejudice with that of Jews. Continues comparison, mentioning the murder of Joe Smith. ]
  - Lydia Maria Child to James Thomas Fields and James Ripley Osgood, 1870 Feb. 3; ALS, 1 p.
    [Requests copies of
    A Romance of the Republic
    and
    The Freedman's Book
    be sent to Mrs. Ellen Crafts or William Crafts. ]
  - Lydia Maria Child to Harriet Jacobson, 1877 Jan 1; APCS, 1 p.
    [Poem beginning, "Another year of setting suns," by J. S. Chadwick. Refers to Jacobson as her "girlfriend."]
  - Lydia Maria Child to "Dear Girl-Friend", 1877 Jan 2; ALS, 3 p.
    [Re her age of 75, loss of husband, and suggestions on how to write.]
  - Lydia Maria Child to Lucretia Mott, n. y. Sep 3; ALS, 3 p.
    [Dislikes compliments or criticism of self and others. Mentions extract relating to Father Mathew and receptions of the
    New York Letters
    for Lucretia Mott. ]
  - Lydia Maria Child to Frances Locke, n. d.; ALS, 2 p.
    [Re gift of inkstand and pen; Refers to an impending trip to England; returns
    "Spirit's Voyage"
    Mentions Mrs. Welles, Mr. Lauriat, Miss Parsons, Franics Locke's sister, Mr. Osgood, and Mr. Thompson.]
  - Lydia Maria Child to Mrs. Bridgman, n. d.; ALS, 1 p.
    [Thank you note; mentions husband.]
  - Lydia Maria Child to James Thomas Fields, n. d.; ALS, 1 p.
    [Sends autograph.]
  - Lydia Maria Child to James Ripley Osgood, n.d.; ALS, 3 p.
    [Letter of introduction for a painter. Mentions anger at a guilty verdict in a murder trial (with the judgment by or on Mr. Colt) and the influence of Penny papers.]
  - Lydia Maria Child to Israel Post, n. d.; ALS, 3 p.
    [Sends article for
    Columbian
    and requests it be sent to Mr. Inman. Suggestions to improve magazine.]
  - Lydia Maria Child to, n. d.; ALS, 1 p.
    [Mentions Ulysses S. Grant. ]
  - Lydia Maria Child to, n. d.; ALS, 1 p.
    [Refers to slavery, and sends article. "Mr. Smith" in very small letters at foot of page.]
- PRINT
  - Lydia Maria Child, n.d.; Print